Mss.B.G78 Mss.B.G78
American Philosophical Society
Asa Gray papers, 1838-1887
Mss.B.G78
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet ca. 100 items
The largest portion of correspondence is with Charles Edwin Bessy on botanical matters, including botanical publications in the United States and Europe, and plants and shell specimens.
Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1957. See in-house shelf list for accession dates and numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
Asa Gray (1810-1888, APS, 1848), Physician, botanist, Harvard professor and an early proponent of the Darwinian theory of Evolution in the United States, was the first American to earn a living as a professional botanist. He made important, lasting contributions to the field of botany, to botanical education, and to the institutionalization of American science.
The son of an Oneida county farmer and tanner in central New York, Asa Gray attended the Fairfield Academy and the Fairfield Medical College, graduating in 1831. After briefly practicing medicine in western New York, he abandoned the profession to pursue research in botany. In 1834 he moved to New York City to study, work and (sometimes) live with John Torrey, then the country’s leading botanist. During an 8-year apprenticeship in which Torrey shared his knowledge and contacts with the young student, their relationship gradually changed from one of student and teacher to that of colleagues who collaborated on many projects. Their most important collaboration was the ground-breaking Flora of North America (1838-1843). From 1836 to 1838 Gray was selected to be the botanist for the U.S. Exploring Expedition, also known as the Wilkes Expedition. Numerous and extended delays caused Gray to resign before the expedition departed in August, 1838. In 1842 he accepted a position as the Fisher Professor of Natural History at Harvard University, and kept it until his death in 1888.
Along with his mentor and co-author John Torrey, Gray introduced a new system of classification already in use in Europe based upon biological similarities, often abandoning the artificial sorting markers of the Linnaean system in favor of natural “type specifications” for the classification of North American flora. This change in biological classification, championed by Torrey and Gray, was critical for bringing the United States into the world scientific community. Gray’s Manual for the Botany of the Northern United States (1848), constituted a natural flora in one volume that was notable for its ease of use, as well as for high standards of accuracy, inclusiveness, and scientific rigor.
Although a Harvard professor for more than 45 years, Gray had less influence as a botanical pedagogue than he did as the author of botany texts. Few of his students became professional botanists; however, his textbooks, especially How Plants Grow and the Manual, greatly increased the popularity of the subject among the lay public. Gray’s many textbooks, from elementary school through the college level introduced thousands of Americans to botany, making it the science of choice in many schools for much of the 19th century. Gray also trained scores of amateur botanists and collectors, raising the standards for how specimens were gathered, labeled, preserved and documented. His corresponded widely with amateurs and paid collectors, who gladly sent him specimens and observations in return for his help with identifications. Gray’s work benefited from his extensive correspondence with collectors throughout North America by greatly expanding the data from which he drew conclusions. The new information and new observations informed his synthetic works such as the Manual, which went through numerous editions. Also, by carefully instructing collectors about what specimens to gather, how to preserve them, and how to label them, Gray insured the quality of his data while modeling a more professional style of botanical work
Doubtless, Gray’s greatest contribution to American Science was his early promotion of Darwinian theory. He had a long standing relationship with Charles Darwin based upon an extended correspondence. Gray was fascinated by Darwin’s thinking and supported him personally and professionally at critical points in his career. Darwin valued Gray’s insights and support, since the American botanist realized even before the publication of the Origin of Species that the issues were both scientific and theological. When a question arose about whether Darwin or Alfred Russell Wallace had originated the notion of natural selection, Darwin’s letters to Gray proved Darwin’s primacy. Gray actively defended Darwin’s ideas in print, endeavoring to insure a fair reception of his work based upon its scientific merit. Gray’s 1860 review of the Origin of Species in the American Journal of Science (2nd series, 29: 153-84), his debates with Louis Agassiz, and his popular essays in the Atlantic Monthly paved the way for broad acceptance of Darwinian evolution in the United States. Gray’s role as an American defender of Darwin’s ideas has been compared to that of Thomas Huxley in Great Britain. But, while Huxley viewed Darwinism as a victory of science over religion, Gray argued for the compatibility of natural selection and Protestant theology. He used natural theology, especially the “argument from design” to affirm that natural selection offers more proof of God’s work in nature. Although Darwin himself eventually arrived at agnostic conclusions, he profoundly appreciated Gray’s work on behalf of his theory, saying that “No one person understands my views and has defended them so well as A. Gray, though he does not by any means go all the way with me. (Letter to James D. Dana, 30 July 1860).
A shy individual, Asa Gray usually worked quietly and steered clear of politics. He received honorary Doctor of Law degrees from Oxford, Cambridge, and Edinburgh and became a member of the American Philosophical Society in 1848. Despite his significance as a botanist and an educator, Gray was little known among historians prior to the publication of A. Hunter Dupree’s major biography Asa Gray: American Botanist, Friend of Darwin. Gray was married to Jane Lathrop Loring, whose social connections brought him into Boston society. The couple were childless. Gray was respected by his peers and fondly remembered as “our greatest botanist” and a “trump of all senses”.
ANB
ILS
Scope and Contents Note
The Asa Gray Papers consist entirely of correspondence between this 19th century American botanist and various (mostly American) correspondents between the years 1838 and 1887. The largest section of this collection of one hundred letters are from Gray to Charles Edwin Bessey, professor of botany at Iowa Agricultural College from 1870-1884, and afterwards professor of botany at the University of Nebraska. Another earlier group of nine letters from 1840 is from Gray to Yale University chemist Benjamin Silliman, publisher of the first American scientific journal. The remainder of the collection consists of correspondence with individuals. These include a September 24, 1839 note to the New York botanist John Torrey (Gray’s mentor), as well as letters to fellow scientists and collectors. For example, his December 31, 1840 letter to Silliman offers an article manuscript for the Journal on Constantine Rafinesque’s botanical writings; another letter to Rev. Porter is a letter of introduction for English botanist Dr. Alexander, seeking housing in Cumberland, MD.; while a circa 1850 note promises to a Mr. Owen fifty copies of Gray’s 1836 textbook, the Elements of Botany. Also, much of the correspondence regards specimens submitted to Gray for identification or other questions of a botanical nature. Some of these letters include an April 18, 1853 letter to Parker Cleaveland, acknowledging receipt of a parcel of multiple specimens such as Persian Lilacs and Chinese Honeysuckle, and an 1871 note to Josiah Hoopes, thanks him for sending Magnolia and [Hydrangea] macrophylla seeds. Other letters answer queries, such as a December 20, 1853 note to Samuel Batchelder, explaining why leaves change color in the autumn, or a March 22, 1883 response to a question from a young student Cora Dike, regarding the location of “auxiliary buds” on Sumach and Honey Locust tree branches. Tables of contents available
Early American History Note
This Collection consists of a variety of correspondence Asa Gray carried on with fellow scientists and collectors in the United States and Europe. Asa Gray was a leading nineteenth American botanist; securing a professorship at Harvard in 1842, he became perhaps the first professional botanist in America. The topic of the letters is almost exclusively botanical in nature. The correspondence includes discussions of publications, current specimens, and fossilized flora. Although Gray carried on extensive correspondence with Charles Darwin, none of that is in this manuscript collection, although the APS does have microfilm of Asa Gray’s correspondence that contains some of this Darwin material.
Bessey, Charles E., (Charles Edwin), 1845-1915; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; James, Thomas Potts, 1803-1882; Ridgely, Charles Goodwin, 1784-1848; Rothrock, Joseph T., 1839-1922; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Vrolik, W., (Willem), 1801-1863; Ward, Henry Augustus, 1834-1906; Botanical gardens.; Botany.; Education -- United States.; Educational Material; Plants -- Collection and preservation.; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Shells.
- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Charles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [May 22]; B G78.1; 5-1/4x3; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Scope and Contents note
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Sent his to Darwin who is working on pollen.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [June 9]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Concerning a paper which will have to be worked up.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [June 10]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Concerning botanical subjects.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, June 14; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. He may keep a copy of the paper.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [July 8?]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. He may keep a copy of the pamphlet.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, July 12; B G78.1; 3x5-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Will receive and enter it.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [Sept. 9]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Thanks for seeds and card.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Sept. 18; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Would like a reprint of an article.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [Sept. 28]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Concerning a new specimen in botany.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [Oct. 16]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Concerning lespedeza.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [Nov. 9]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Thanks for specimen.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, [Nov. 20]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and end. Reports that he is doing very well.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Would like some of the polygonums.
    General note
    Unlocated 3/11
  - Letter to [Moncure Daniel?] Conway, Oct. 30; B G78.1; 6x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning the correct name of a tree.
  - Letter to H. R. Hawes, Oct. 7; B G78.1; 6x3-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Will be pleased to meet him.
  - Letter to Mr. Winsor, Jan. 31; B G78.1; 5-3/4x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. Invitation to dinner.
  - Asa Gray to L.E.W. Eaton, April 6; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - A[sa] Gray to Mr Pratt, undated; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to "Dear Alice", B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, Monday evening. A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Oct. 28, [1871?]; B G78.1; 4x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning botanical matters.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, April 16, [1882?]; B G78.1; 7-1/2x4-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Friendly letter. Concerning a correction for Alvord's article.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Lincoln, Neb., Dec. 5, [1884]; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Has ordered publication from England for him.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Lincoln, Neb., March 9, [1885]; B G78.1; 3x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Sends news of cost of publication, according to J. D. Hooker.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s [Goodwin] Ridgeley, Brooklyn, Feb. 7, 1838; B G78.1; 9-1/2x8; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Lists scientific instruments necessary for the expedition.
  - Correspondence with C.E. Bessey, etc., 1838-1887; B G78.1; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. 62 items (letters and postal cards) and 3 engravings, plus one newspaper clipping. Various sizes. Contains 3 letters not by Asa Gray. See table of contents.
  - [Asa] Gray to [John Torrey], 1839 Sept 24; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - A[sa] Gray to J[ohn] J[oseph] Bennett, 1845 April 30; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to Mr. Owen, 1850?; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    [ca.]. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning the sale of texts.
  - A[sa] Gray to [Parker] Cleavland, 1853 April 18; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Tho[mas] P[otts] James to [Asa] Gray, 1855 Dec 18
  - A[sa] Gray to [TP] James, 1855 Nov 12; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to [Willem] Vrolik, May 4, 1858; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Introduces A. A. Gould.
  - Asa Gray to Professor Rogers, 1860 Jan 27; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - A[sa] Gray to [Joseph Trimble] Rothrock, 1864 Oct 28; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Asa Gray to [John Edward?] Gray, 1869 October 19; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s E[dwin] Bessey, Jan. 13, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Recommends book for use in school.
  - Letter to [Charles E. Bessey], May 24, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning botany in America.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, July 22, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin Bessey], Oct. 16, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning a botanical matter.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Nov. 5, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for plants. Concerning their growth.
  - Letter to [Henry Augustus] Ward, July 11, 1870; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning botanical knowledge.
  - Asa Gray to [Josiah] Hoopes, 1871 March 18; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, July 20, 1871; B G78.1; 8x4-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his article on a plant.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, March 11, 1872; B G78.1; 6x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Asks if he can furnish plants and seeds for a man in England.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Aug. 17, 1872; B G78.1; 10-1/2x8; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Denver, A.L.S. 1p. Asks that they meet in Dubuque.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin Bessey], Sept. 7, 1872; B G78.1; 5-1/2x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Botanical news.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Oct. 24, 1872; B G78.1; 6x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, L.S.: Asa Gray pr. Sereno Watson. 1p. Concerning cypripediums.
    - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Sept. 13, 1872; B G78.1; 4-3/4x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
      Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Asks for certain nuts which he can collect.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, July 13, 1872; B G78.1; 8x5; Watson, Sereno, 1826-1892.
    Cambridge, A.L.S.for A[sa] Gray. 1p. and end. Concerning Asa Gray. Botanical news.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, March 10, 1873; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Will let him have a book which he purchased.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, May 14, 1873; B G78.1; 9x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Friendly letter. Concerning a botanical term.
  - A[sa] Gray to [Alonzo Howard] Clark, 1873 July 5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Asa Gray to Dr Carruthers, 1874 May 2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Aug. 21, 1874; B G78.1; 5-3/4x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Asks for plants and seeds.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Dec. 15, 1874; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Enc.of 3 cards introducing Bessey to C. L. Anderson, E. L. Greene, and Dr. and Mrs. Hewston. Knows that he will enjoy his California visit. Tells him sights to see and encloses cards introducing him to various people.
  - Letter to [Charles E.] Bessey, March 20, 1875; B G78.1; 5-1/2x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning lespedeza.
  - Letter to J. C. Arthur, March 7, 1876; B G78.1; 8x5; E[ngelmann], G[eorge], 1809-1884.
    St. Louis, A.L.S. with initials. 4p. Concerning botany of the U.S. Sent lespedeza to Gray.
  - Letter to [Charles E.] Bessey, June 13, 1876; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and add. and enc. of 1p. Concerning a botanical problem which J. D. Hooker helped solve. Forwards ad of new publication on botany of California.
  - Asa Gry to [George Edward?] Ellis, 1877 May 9; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, May 13, 1877; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Concerning botanical news for a publication.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, 1877 June 17; B G78.1; 5-1/4x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Enc. wanting. Forwards part of Darwin's letter and he wants it returned.
  - Asa Gray to Mr Crandall, 1877 June 21; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Jan. 30, 1878; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning a problem in botany.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Feb. 4, 1878; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning botanical matters.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, June 4, 1878; B G78.1; 3x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. Concerning botanical publications.
  - Letter to [Charles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, June 14, 1878; B G78.1; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his request for a publication.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, July 15, 1878; B G78.1; 3x5-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and end. Will forward publications.
  - Note to C[harles] A[sic] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, July 15, 1878; B G78.1; 3x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.N.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Thank you note.
  - Letter to M[oncure] D[aniel] Conway, May 22, 1879; B G78.1; 3x4-3/4; Bunsen, [Robert Wilhelm] E[berhard] von, 1811- 1899.
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Will try to see him tomorrow afternoon.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Feb. 29, 1880; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Asks that he fill out item and return it to him.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Jan. 12, 1882; B G78.1; 3x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Makes no announcement quite yet, but will before long.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey Ames, Iowa, March 28, 1882; B G78.1; 6x3-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning an article on the compass plant written by Alvord.
  - Letter to C[harles] E[dwin] Bessey, Ames, April 7, 1882; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning the article by Alvord on the compass plant.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Ames, Iowa, Nov. 8, 1882; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning the American naturalist's articles from private correspondence.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Oct. 1, 1884; B G78.1; 8-1/4x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning his "little book." Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Dr. Dawson, July 9, 1884; B G78.1; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Will visit with them.
  - Letter to Mr. Bistite(?), June 21, 1885; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning the shamrock.
  - Letter to Medfield, Dec. 24, 1886; B G78.1; 6x4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Thanks for his photograph.
  - Letter to [Charles Edwin] Bessey, Feb. 4, 1887; B G78.1; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
  - Letter to B[enjamin] Silliman, Jr., Feb. 9, [1840]; B G78.2; 8-1/4x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Friendly letter. Pertaining to the tea plant.
  - Letter to B[enjamin] Silliman, New Haven, Jan. 31, 1840; B G78.2; 10x8-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Botanical news.
  - Letter to Benj[amin] Silliman, New Haven, June, 1840; B G78.2; 10x7-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Friendly letter. Congratulates him on his marriage.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, Sept. 7, 1840; B G78.2; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning his article.
  - Letter to Benj[amin] Silliman, New Haven, Oct. 5, 1840; B G78.2; 10x7-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Concerning his article. Friendly letter. News of Rafinesque's death.
  - Letter to Benj[amin] Silliman, New Haven, Nov. 15, 1840; B G78.2; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Business. Concerning the elogue on Rafinesque.
  - Letter to Benj[amin] Silliman, New Haven, Nov. 30, 1840; B G78.2; 10-1/2x8-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Business.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, Dec. 31, 1840; B G78.2; 10x7-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning an article of his on Rafinesque.
  - Letters to Mrs. and Benjamin Silliman, 1840-1864; B G78.2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    A.L.S. 9 items. Various sizes. To B.Silliman: Jan.31; Feb.30; [June]; Sept. 7; Oct. 5; Nov. 15; Nov. 30; Dec. 31; 1840; and to Mrs. Silliman, Nov.4,1864. Table of contents available.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah Isabella McClellan Webb] Silliman, Nov. 4, 1864; B G78.2; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Thanks for seeds. Refers to Benjamin Silliman and A. A. Gould.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l Batchelder, Dec. 20, 1853; B G78.3; 8x5; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Concerning the change in color of leaves, in the autumn.
  - Letter to Nehemiah Cleaveland, June 21, 1851; B G78.4; 10x7-3/4; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888